<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Daddy and the kids</title>
	<subtitle></subtitle>
	<link href="https://www.daddyandthekids.com/feed.xml" rel="self"/>
	<link href="https://www.daddyandthekids.com/"/>
	
	<updated>2021-06-22T02:00:00+02:00</updated>
	
	<id>https://www.daddyandthekids.com</id>
	<author>
  <name>Dominic</name>
  <email>ds@kammamuri.com</email>
	</author>
	
  
  <entry>
    <title>How Do You Fix A Spoiled Child? Framework &amp; 10 Steps To Make It Happen.</title>
    <link href="https://www.daddyandthekids.com/posts/how-do-you-fix-a-aspoiled-child/"/>
    <updated>2021-06-30T02:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>https://www.daddyandthekids.com/posts/how-do-you-fix-a-aspoiled-child/</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[
      <h2>How Can You Unspoil Your Kids?</h2>
<p><img src="/images/How-Do-You-Fix-A-Spoiled-Child.jpg" alt="How-Do-You-Fix-A-Spoiled-Child" title="Credits to Nathan Dumlao on https://unsplash.com/photos/Y-H5pu2oglE "></p>
<p>Kids are exposed to and influenced by a lot of things, more than we could ever imagine.</p>
<p>Children may pick up behaviors from observing adults and peers, or from what they see on television. Sometimes we are too tired after work to set rules and so we indulge for a moment to every request they have.
Parents, of course, play a major role in this.</p>
<p>In every day life, it’s hard to tell whether you’re spoiling your kids, but when they start to show signs of ungrateful behavior and frequent tantrums, the evidence is unmistakable.
<strong>It might be time for you to teach them all about gratitude again!</strong></p>
<p>This article will provide a few pointers on how to do so successfully and get their attention in a way that helps them internalize the frustration of a &quot;no&quot;, to help them grow stronger.</p>
<h2>You may also want to check some helpful books about this subject:</h2>
<!-- <a target="_blank"  href="https://www.amazon.co.uk/gp/product/1848123094/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&camp=1634&creative=6738&creativeASIN=1848123094&linkCode=as2&tag=dominic8004-21&linkId=af22fc637e39971360f4f6437cfdcdb4"><img border="0" src="//ws-eu.amazon-adsystem.com/widgets/q?_encoding=UTF8&MarketPlace=GB&ASIN=1848123094&ServiceVersion=20070822&ID=AsinImage&WS=1&Format=_SL160_&tag=dominic8004-21" ></a> -->
<p><a href="https://amzn.to/3iWXYPJ">How To Talk So Kids Will Listen and Listen So Kids Will Talk</a>  by Adele Faber.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>This book is really helpful for anything related to good communication with your kids. I read it twice and also borrowed it from my local library to take more notes. Number one.</p>
</blockquote>
<!-- <a target="_blank"  href="https://www.amazon.co.uk/gp/product/0399184864/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&camp=1634&creative=6738&creativeASIN=0399184864&linkCode=as2&tag=dominic8004-21&linkId=e7e19d54aa0c2c16dfbc3bb8b075c92b"><img border="0" src="//ws-eu.amazon-adsystem.com/widgets/q?_encoding=UTF8&MarketPlace=GB&ASIN=0399184864&ServiceVersion=20070822&ID=AsinImage&WS=1&Format=_SL160_&tag=dominic8004-21" ></a> -->
<p><a href="https://amzn.to/3zMfnSa">The Me, Me, Me Epidemic: A Step-by-Step Guide to Raising Capable, Grateful Kids in an Over-Entitled World</a></p>
<blockquote>
<p>A general approch to raise healthy humans, with practical tips.</p>
</blockquote>
<!-- <a target="_blank"  href="https://www.amazon.co.uk/gp/product/0062247026/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&camp=1634&creative=6738&creativeASIN=0062247026&linkCode=as2&tag=dominic8004-21&linkId=d4ccc59974598526fe3c5e20280e582e"><img border="0" src="//ws-eu.amazon-adsystem.com/widgets/q?_encoding=UTF8&MarketPlace=GB&ASIN=0062247026&ServiceVersion=20070822&ID=AsinImage&WS=1&Format=_SL160_&tag=dominic8004-21" ></a> -->
<p><a href="https://amzn.to/3BI4wKy">The Opposite of Spoiled: Raising Kids Who Are Grounded, Generous, and Smart About Money</a></p>
<!-- <a target="_blank"  href="https://www.amazon.co.uk/gp/product/0345548043/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&camp=1634&creative=6738&creativeASIN=0345548043&linkCode=as2&tag=dominic8004-21&linkId=697b34e89b7f5b8b6afa3009712e6b56"><img border="0" src="//ws-eu.amazon-adsystem.com/widgets/q?_encoding=UTF8&MarketPlace=GB&ASIN=0345548043&ServiceVersion=20070822&ID=AsinImage&WS=1&Format=_SL160_&tag=dominic8004-21" ></a> -->
<p><a href="https://amzn.to/3xbtIpt">No-Drama Discipline: The Whole-Brain Way to Calm the Chaos and Nurture Your Child's Developing Mind</a></p>
<blockquote>
<p>Focused on positive parenting.</p>
</blockquote>
<!-- <a target="_blank"  href="https://www.amazon.co.uk/gp/product/1402242069/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&camp=1634&creative=6738&creativeASIN=1402242069&linkCode=as2&tag=dominic8004-21&linkId=3f657e7c9feb1c9bc8b60a1035b927c6"><img border="0" src="//ws-eu.amazon-adsystem.com/widgets/q?_encoding=UTF8&MarketPlace=GB&ASIN=1402242069&ServiceVersion=20070822&ID=AsinImage&WS=1&Format=_SL160_&tag=dominic8004-21" ></a> -->
<p><a href="https://amzn.to/2WuhZFP">How to Unspoil Your Child Fast: A Speedy, Complete Guide to Contented Children and Happy Parents</a></p>
<blockquote>
<p>Appreciated by most, critiqued by someone who thinks his methods are not focused on positive parenting but more on severity, consequences and raising little soldiers. Truth often lies in the middle.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>——</p>
<p>Spoiled children are really annoying and disturbing.
If you are the father of a child who was born with a  <strong>silver spoon in their mouth</strong> , then you probably experienced embarrassment among your friends and relatives when they made a scene in front of everybody.</p>
<p>If you continue in this manner, these kids will grow up to be entitled brats that will definitely annoy everyone around them.</p>
<p>There are two ways you can approach the situation when your child is displaying spoiled behavior. You can either let it go, or try to fix it. Fixing a bad behavior is harder, and causes a lot of stress, but only for a short timer. Your future self will be grateful for your effort not allowing things to go downhill.</p>
<p>My kids know that I am strict about how I expect them to act and behave. Being strict does not absolutely mean that you must be physically or mentally violent towards your kids. It means that you are firm in your decision to make them well-behaved individuals who don’t give in to doing things just because they could.</p>
<p><strong>TL;DR: Try to be</strong> <strong>Firm, Sweet and Gentle with your kids.</strong>  And many problems will fly away!</p>
<h2>Framework To Fix A Spolied Child</h2>
<p>Before you fix your spoiled kid you have to check if you have a good setting, so analyse deeply your situation and try to build a good supportive framework for the change to happen easily.</p>
<h3>1. Think about your own mistakes as an adult</h3>
<p>The first step to fix a spoiled kid is <strong>focusing on our behaviour as a parent</strong>. Critical situations are the first ones to analyse, but every day life is important too.</p>
<p>Are we saying &quot;yes&quot; to everything they ask to us? Are we using any kind of reward system? Is there a punishment system? Are we playing favorites? Are we over-reacting to everything they do and then feel guilty about it?</p>
<p>Sometimes we are too tired to say &quot;no&quot; and give in to their demands. Kids learn quickly that if they insist enough, you will capitulate and change your no to a yes. And that's the first step to creating a spoiled child. So before you fix your kid's behaviour, you have to look at yourself and admit that you may be part of the problem. Think well before deciding to say yes or no.</p>
<p>Set the rules when you are relaxed. Then, in critical situations, STOP and think: &quot;Should I say yes or no according to the rules?&quot; Then follow along and don't change your mind. Your kids will respect you more if you are kind but firm. Kids need some boundaries for them to become more independent but responsible. If you give in to them every time they ask, they will feel as if they can rule over you, but their frontal lobes are not yet developed enough to filter out their emotional responses to their commands.</p>
<h3>2. Encourage them to take sports or activities that have rules</h3>
<p>Sports can do wonders to kids, but you must choose carefully. The coach is really really important, it can save or destroy a kid self esteem. Ask other parents, know your neighbourhoods. My son takes judo lessons and the sensei is a really great man: wise, nice but firm. He can make children respect the rules. Kids love and respect him. I saw a terrible, annoying, spoiled kid in the same class as my son, who was literally transformed during the year, and his mom is eternally grateful to the coach, because the child learned 3 important lessons: being patient, waiting for his turn, and being aware of others.</p>
<p>Spoiled kids are often selfish about their needs, or they want to draw attention. That' why also team sports are helpful, because everyone has a role, you play for your team. So in a family you should try to teach your kids that they also play &quot; for the family team&quot;.</p>
<h3>3. Model good behavior in front of them</h3>
<p>I talked to a psychologist on the phone and parents had the same problem: what to do with my spoiled kid? The answer is really surprising. If you are asking yourself that question you are probably guilty of spoiling your kid. She said: mom and dad are like kids as well, we do all the mistakes, we all want the best for our children and sometimes we act like spoiled kids ourselves. But as grown up adults we have to live with it and understand that our kids learn by example.</p>
<p>When you are a model of good behavior in front of them, they will follow you. A good way to do that is with consistency: make sure that your kids see you doing the right thing and they will copy you. No-one is perfect and we may lose our temper sometimes, don't be afraid to apologise if you make a mistake. Your kids will learn from this too.</p>
<h3>4. Be consistent with consequences and limits</h3>
<p>Write down some rules for your kids. Be careful, the list should be short but precise, and remember to keep a copy of it to reference whenever necessary. Rules may change over time as they grow up or as new situations happen. Sit down with them and write 3 non-negotiable rules. Then ask them to help you finding ideas for rules that may be important to follow in the house. It can be really educational to do so. They will be more prone to follow the rules.</p>
<p>Try to involve your spose too. You must find a common idea of what can be done and what not. Often spoiled kids find the weakest parent and exploit him/her to get what they want. It's a tactic that these little monsters :-) use to avoid getting disciplined. This is why your rules must be clear and consistent. When your kids are too young, you will have to set the limit for some of their activities. If at an early age they learn to respect the limits, they will not become spoiled when they are older. You and your spose should work together.</p>
<h2>What Steps Do I take To Unspoil My Child?</h2>
<p>Here are the basic steps that I take in order to help my kids become responsible adults who are grateful for everything they have:</p>
<ol>
<li>
<p>Make sure they understand that <strong>they can ask for help</strong> or be told what is expected of them if they need assistance with a certain task.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Show empathy</strong> and tell them that you know how hard it is to want something and not being able to get it. Tell them you appreciate the effort they will make to give up their really desired toy. Also, <strong>dont' say a definitive no</strong>. One thing that really works for me is <strong>writing their desire down on paper</strong>. It does work really well. I say &quot; I know you want X a lot. Let's wirte it down for later / for Santa / for your birthday, so we don't forget it&quot;. This is usually enough to calm them and give them hope that what they want will arrive sooner or later. Kids learn patience this way, and this is a good path to getting unspoiled. Do not use this pattern to much, or it will lose power. Use it sparingly, though.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Make sure your home atmosphere is one where <strong>they are allowed to play and have fun without being given too many restrictions</strong> on what they can and cannot do. Write down the most important rules in a positive way. Instead of &quot; Don't play with the ball in side the house&quot;, try &quot;We can use the ball only in the garden!&quot;</p>
</li>
</ol>
<p>You want to** set the right example** for them. But it is important that you let them enjoy your company, without yelling &quot;STOP IT&quot; every minute or so.</p>
<ol start="4">
<li>
<p>As you sit and chat with your children, be sure to <strong>praise them for their good behavior</strong>. They need to know that you’re proud of them for having good manners.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Provide clear expectations</strong> so your children know what you are expecting from them.
Make your kids accountable for organizing a certain chore or assign them some responsibility they can manage in relation to their age.
Make sure everyone knows who is responsible for what and which tasks are important, without being too obsessive. You don't want to raise your kids in a  <strong>Full Metal Jacket camp</strong> .</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>If they start to display spoiled behavior, <strong>calmly isolate them and talk to them in a soft but firm way</strong>. Make them think about how they should’ve behaved. If they keep answering unpolitely tell the how they can tell the same thing in a gentle way. If they yell &quot; I Want Candies!!&quot; tell them : &quot; You should say with a calm tone  Dad Can I have some candies please?&quot;</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Anticipate what it's going to happen.</strong> If you take them to the supermarket, before you go in say something like: &quot;Remember, we are here only to buy something for dinner, there are a lot of cool things in the supermarket but we don't need them now, did you understand? Can you promise me you will be a good boy?&quot;</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>If your child is constantly being rebellious or misbehaves, you may want to <strong>consider finding an educator</strong> for some time. Spoiled kids usually feel a sense of awe of unrelated people. You need someone who can be firm with them, yet also give them the loving support they require.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Discipline</strong> is essential for teaching and molding your children into well-behaved and mature individuals. If you want to be able to teach them how to be grateful and appreciative for the things they are given, you must first show them what this looks like through the way you carry yourself and your interactions with others.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Make sure that when you are disciplining your children, you are <strong>not using any types of physical abuse</strong> because this will only confuse them about what’s right or wrong. And remember that  <strong>words and non-verbal communication can wound and hurt like the physical counterpart.</strong></p>
</li>
</ol>
<h2>Conclusion</h2>
<p>There are a lot of ways to help your children get on the right path and avoid spoiling them. The best thing you can do is using the right tools and tactics in order to raise a disciplined child that will be ready for the world.</p>
<p>Sometimes the path seems long and hard, but it is still worth walking. If you can get a few lessons from other parents who have already walked along the same path, you will soon be able to see how to do things right and avoid spoiling your children.</p>
<p>Your family has a chance to raise a child that will become a great adult someday. Can you act soon and correct any mistake before they grow up? I think so, and I hope that this article gives you a little insight.</p>
<p>I know people are different and that's what makes life interesting.
But spolied kids usually become insecure adults who often can't take criticism, who are not very independent. They may also give up too quickly or fall more easily into despair over disappointments because they are used to hear YES over and over to their requests.</p>
<p>In extreme cases they'll never learn to appreciate anything because it's so easy for them to fall into the habit of demanding everything from other people and being dissatisfied with whatever they receive. This is how cruel life really is in the universe of spoiled humanhood.</p>
<p>So take care of your kids and raise them properly if you want them to change their lives for the better.</p>

    ]]></content>
  </entry>
	
  
  <entry>
    <title>11 Things All Dads Wish Their Kids Knew Before They Grow Up - Life Lessons Every Kid Should Learn (with book selection)</title>
    <link href="https://www.daddyandthekids.com/posts/11-things-all-dads-wish-their-kids-knew-before-they-grow-up/"/>
    <updated>2021-06-29T02:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>https://www.daddyandthekids.com/posts/11-things-all-dads-wish-their-kids-knew-before-they-grow-up/</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[
      <p><img src="/images/11-things-all-dads-wish-their-kids-knew-before-they-grow-up.jpg" alt="Life Lessons Every Kid Should Know" title="Credits to Frame Harirak on https://unsplash.com/photos/Ei_lQ6kTwiI "></p>
<p><strong>Fathers love their kids</strong>, and this love is often expressed in the form of advice. The following are some pieces of advice that many dads wish their kids knew before they grow up.</p>
<p>I collected this tips asking deeply to myself, in the first place, and then asking every father I know. The most helpful tips came from grandfathers, who are fathers to the power of 2.</p>
<h2>1. Just try to be the best person you can be, and then forgive yourself when you fail.</h2>
<p><strong>Life is full of ups and downs</strong>. This means that no matter what you're going through right now, no matter how terrible your situation is, there's always a way to be your best self. It's up to you to figure out what that is and go about it in a way where you're constantly trying to improve yourself. When you face a bad situation or a stressful moment, thinking about the best version of yourself will help you in many ways, because <strong>you'll act like a superhero</strong> would act in that situation, not the way you usually are. You'll always be thinking about doing your best, even though it's unlikely for you to always do your best every single time.</p>
<p>At the same time, <strong>many people find it very difficult to forgive themselves when they fail at something</strong>. Typically this is due to the fear of losing or being mocked by others in some way or another for doing something wrong. Because of this, many people are less likely to try new things if they are not confident in themselves.</p>
<p>One way to deal with the fear that causes this is through self-compassion. This can be achieved by providing yourself with compassion when you make mistakes, rather than holding onto the shame that comes along with making a mistake. Forgiving yourself also provides a sense of relief and helps you move on from the mistake without feeling regretful about it's outcome.</p>
<p>Science shows that people who can forgive themselves for their errors are more likely to accomplish original things and to get unstuck in difficult times. They also enjoy more the journey and the experimentation while not being 100% focused on the outcome.
This is one of the best advice I can give to my kids.</p>
<p>Like a said in another post, you'll <a href="/posts/how-to-raise-smart-kids/">grow smarter kids</a> , if you show them <a href="https://www.businessinsider.com/12-ways-to-raise-smarter-more-successful-and-happier-kids-2019-8?r=US&amp;IR=T#2-show-them-how-to-embrace-mistakes-2">how to embrace mistakes</a> &quot;embrace mistakes&quot;) .</p>
<h3>Suggested readings:</h3>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://amzn.to/3jCncEK">How To Stop Worrying And Start Living</a></li>
</ul>
<p><a href="https://amzn.to/3jCncEK"><img src="https://www.amazon.co.uk/images/I/51Ci2yl0UkL._SY291_BO1,204,203,200_QL40_ML2_.jpg" alt="How To Stop Worrying And Start Living"></a></p>
<blockquote>
<p>Classic book from Dale Carnagie. Less popular than &quot;How to Win Friends and Influence People&quot; but worth a read.</p>
</blockquote>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://amzn.to/3t4PIBT">Awaken The Giant Within</a></li>
</ul>
<p><a href="https://amzn.to/3t4PIBT"><img src="https://www.amazon.co.uk/images/I/51z3Mb1q0QL._SY291_BO1,204,203,200_QL40_ML2_.jpg" alt="Awaken The Giant Within"></a></p>
<blockquote>
<p>Tony Robbins is a legend in the self help category. With his great charisma and attitude he has the ability to motivate and empower anyone.</p>
</blockquote>
<h2>2. Keep your promises and be honest.</h2>
<p>Do what you say you will do. <strong>Never make excuses.</strong> Stop making excuses for why you couldn't do something, or why you weren’t able to accomplish something. If you make a promise, make sure you are going to stick to it. Don’t give excuses about why you couldn’t make it. Don’t put things off for later; do them now. Being reliable and trustworthy is so important, and making excuses makes your will power weaker, no matter what the excuse is. Honesty, on the same level is important because your destiny is in your hands.</p>
<h2>3. Respect nature and its gifts.</h2>
<p>Nature is all around you, so don't forget that you're a part of it.  Appreciate that these things are part of your life too. Give nature a little extra attention whenever you can, and talk about it with your kids.</p>
<h2>4. Be grateful</h2>
<p>Be grateful everyday for what you have, even if it’s simple. Never take the little things for granted, because when you’re older, you’ll realize how important they were to you.</p>
<p><strong>Happiness is in the small things</strong>. Big wins produce a short lasting happiness due to the phenomenon known as Hedonic Adaptation, which is the tendency of humanity to quickly go back to our normal, stable level of happiness, even after big recent positive or negative life events. So for example, as we make more money, our expectations and desires rise too. This then results in no permanent gain in happiness.</p>
<p>But being grateful for small victories will create a feeling of being successful that will last longer.</p>
<p><strong>Research showed the benefits of gratitude</strong>, and more and more authors, bloggers and youtubers have now started a trend. But the practice of gratitude can really be transformational, if consistent.</p>
<p>References:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p><a href="https://www.health.harvard.edu/healthbeat/giving-thanks-can-make-you-happier">Giving thanks can make you happier -- Harvard Health</a></p>
</li>
<li>
<p><a href="https://www.forbes.com/sites/amymorin/2014/11/23/7-scientifically-proven-benefits-of-gratitude-that-will-motivate-you-to-give-thanks-year-round/">Proven benefits of Gratitude</a></p>
</li>
<li>
<p><a href="https://positivepsychology.com/benefits-gratitude-research-questions/">28 Benefits of Gratitude &amp; Most Significant Research Findings</a></p>
</li>
</ul>
<h3>Suggested readings:</h3>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://amzn.to/3Bvl2g6">The Little Book of Gratitude</a></li>
</ul>
<p><a href="https://amzn.to/3Bvl2g6"><img src="https://www.amazon.co.uk/images/I/51JUeOTaK3L._SY291_BO1,204,203,200_QL40_ML2_.jpg" alt="The Little Book of Gratitude"></a></p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://amzn.to/3BvDJAj">The Psychology of Gratitude</a></li>
</ul>
<p><a href="https://amzn.to/3BvDJAj"><img src="https://www.amazon.co.uk/images/I/41xv6fmx1lL._SY291_BO1,204,203,200_QL40_ML2_.jpg" alt="The Psychology of Gratitude"></a></p>
<blockquote>
<p>More expensive but for a reason: in depht scientific research about gratitude by Ph.D. Robert Emmons and Michael McCullough.</p>
</blockquote>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://amzn.to/3BuG4LS">Thanks!: How Practicing Gratitude Can Make You Happier</a></li>
</ul>
<p><a href="https://amzn.to/3BuG4LS"><img src="https://www.amazon.co.uk/images/I/41vxylGAy1L._SY291_BO1,204,203,200_QL40_ML2_.jpg" alt="Thanks!: How Practicing Gratitude Can Make You Happier"></a></p>
<blockquote>
<p>This is the divulgative version of the book above, by Robert Emmons.</p>
</blockquote>
<h2>5. Kindness pays off in the long run</h2>
<p>Don’t be mean to people or animals; even if you don’t like them.</p>
<p><strong>Be nice and kind to everyone</strong>, even those who are not nice or kind in return. You will have so much benefit from this, maybe later in your life. You may not believe in Karma, but there is some kind of positive energy that accumulates in you by being kind.</p>
<p>Do you remember the famous Aesop's fable, &quot;The Lion and The Mouse&quot; ?
An act of kindness to someone now, can pay a lot in the future, who knows.</p>
<h3>Suggested readings:</h3>
<!-- 
<a target="_blank" href="https://www.amazon.co.uk/gp/product/0143129279/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&camp=1634&creative=6738&creativeASIN=0143129279&linkCode=as2&tag=dominic8004-21&linkId=a536eb1a78cde019548c4c3632818f66">The Power of Kindness: The Unexpected Benefits of Leading a Compassionate Life</a>

<a target="_blank"  href="https://www.amazon.co.uk/gp/product/0143129279/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&camp=1634&creative=6738&creativeASIN=0143129279&linkCode=as2&tag=dominic8004-21&linkId=adfdbfe72b0fbafaebacc28738892f5a"><img border="0" src="//ws-eu.amazon-adsystem.com/widgets/q?_encoding=UTF8&MarketPlace=GB&ASIN=0143129279&ServiceVersion=20070822&ID=AsinImage&WS=1&Format=_SL250_&tag=dominic8004-21" ></a>


<a target="_blank" href="https://www.amazon.co.uk/gp/product/1928832008/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&camp=1634&creative=6738&creativeASIN=1928832008&linkCode=as2&tag=dominic8004-21&linkId=b33cb50edf21f79e7fa403dd0de3a431">The Hidden Power of Kindness: A Practical Handbook for Souls Who Dare to Transform the World, One Deed at a Time</a>


<a target="_blank"  href="https://www.amazon.co.uk/gp/product/1928832008/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&camp=1634&creative=6738&creativeASIN=1928832008&linkCode=as2&tag=dominic8004-21&linkId=ed6c0dc6f84efd8c9c7daaa6218dd62b"><img border="0" src="//ws-eu.amazon-adsystem.com/widgets/q?_encoding=UTF8&MarketPlace=GB&ASIN=1928832008&ServiceVersion=20070822&ID=AsinImage&WS=1&Format=_SL250_&tag=dominic8004-21" ></a> -->
<h2>5. Don't give up on your dreams, even in the face of adversity.</h2>
<p><strong>Consistency is the real superpower</strong>. Never give up and be antifragile. Learn from mistakes and  get up again  when you are knocked down.</p>
<p>If we can be consistent in our actions, then success will follow. We must decide what success looks like and then &quot;just do it&quot;. Consistency is key. It’s easy to say that you will do something, but it’s not so easy to actually do it. To make sure you reach your goal, you have to be consistent in what you are doing and remind yourself why you want to achieve the goal that you set out for yourself. Think about your goal every day.</p>
<!-- <iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/BBQb1SVPboI" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe> -->
<p>Thanks to <strong>the power of the compounding effect</strong>, little by little you will go very far, in exponential increments!</p>
<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/qDxDCtZ9UkE" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe>
<h2>6. Don't be a follower, always be a leader</h2>
<p>It’s OK for you to feel different  from the other kids around you, no one else is exactly like you. No one else can be you because everyone has their own unique story, perspective and struggle that make them who they are to others and to themselves.
<strong>It's Ok to be you</strong>.</p>
<p>Don't waste your time waiting for someone else to make a change or do something first. <strong>You are responsible for your own happiness and life</strong>. Don't rely on others to do that for you. Teach your kids to take control of their life and to stop putting in the work when it's not worth.  Diy also.
If you're not happy with your life, don't stay still, but rather move towards something that excites and engages you. Happiness is a journey, not a destination.</p>
<h2>7. Learn to let go</h2>
<p><strong>It's okay to let go of something that doesn't work out</strong>. Everyone has to learn that sometimes the thing you want most is not the right thing for you. Sometimes, what we want may not actually be good for us. It can be challenging to learn it too late in life because people are usually stuck with a certain perspective. So the earlier that we learn this lesson, the better.</p>
<p>It’s more about your attitude towards things than the thing itself. Everyone wants to see good results in life because everyone has their own different dream and objective, but even if you don't achieve those goals sometimes, it doesn't mean that you failed at the process or at your life. You’ve just learned a lesson from it—and you can apply this lesson to help you achieve another goal in your future instead. Also avoid negative people, they can have a bad influence over you, so just move on.</p>
<h2>8. Money is not all</h2>
<p>When you get older you will look back and realize what really matters in life, money is not it.
There are <strong>certain things that money can't buy</strong> and the greatest gift you can give someone is your time. Give it freely and lovingly. Time spent with family, friends and loved ones. Time spent doing things you've always wanted to do but never dreamed possible.</p>
<p>Even if money and higher incomes are in general associated with higher experienced well being and life satisfaction ( see PNAS <a href="https://www.pnas.org/content/118/4/e2016976118">Experienced well-being rises with income</a>  ), money won't give you happiness. Due to Hedonic adaptation, stuff will soon lose its initial impact on you.
In the long run, people who have money and plenty of average experiences will be no happier than those who are poor but had many good experiences.</p>
<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/juO4zxsjSjw" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe>
<h2>9. Your Family will help you</h2>
<p><strong>Keep your siblings close and don't fight</strong> with them. Your family is the first place in your life where you can find help. When you need it, you can always go to your family and they will always be there for you.</p>
<h2>10. Don't sweat the small stuff. It's no big deal.</h2>
<p><strong>Don't try to over-optimize things</strong> because sometime you waste a lot of energy on useless tweaks and lose the big picture. Don't worry about things you can't control. The things you can influence should be your major concern.</p>
<p>Don't be afraid to take risks. Don't torture yourself with guilt. You're allowed to make mistakes as long as you learn from them and improve for next time. Don't waste time worrying about what other people are doing. Who cares? Stay focused on what you're doing and let them do what they want to do, regardless of how it might affect you or your work.</p>
<p>It's OK to quit something that doesn't make sense.
Learn when to quit.
<a href="https://medium.com/thrive-global/when-is-it-time-to-quit-something-1b7d9e9eab4f"> When Is It Time to Quit Something | by Ankurman Shrestha | Thrive Global | Medium</a></p>
<h3>Suggested reading:</h3>
<!-- 
<a target="_blank" href="https://www.amazon.co.uk/gp/product/0340708018/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&camp=1634&creative=6738&creativeASIN=0340708018&linkCode=as2&tag=dominic8004-21&linkId=b3e2fb401e526fe62f8ea2fa36f685df">Don't Sweat the Small Stuff: Simple ways to Keep the Little Things from Overtaking Your Life: Simple Ways to Keep the Little Things from Taking Over Your Life</a>

<a target="_blank"  href="https://www.amazon.co.uk/gp/product/0340708018/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&camp=1634&creative=6738&creativeASIN=0340708018&linkCode=as2&tag=dominic8004-21&linkId=ca41b592f6900dca98a380c9b7b53d90"><img border="0" src="//ws-eu.amazon-adsystem.com/widgets/q?_encoding=UTF8&MarketPlace=GB&ASIN=0340708018&ServiceVersion=20070822&ID=AsinImage&WS=1&Format=_SL250_&tag=dominic8004-21" ></a> -->
<blockquote>
<p>After almost two decades since the original release of Don't Sweat the Small Stuff, Richard Carlson's insights on the meaning of life continue to be timeless. The book teaches us to focus on the 'now' and find balance by living through contentment. ― <strong>Deepak Chopra</strong></p>
</blockquote>
<h2>11. Smile more.</h2>
<p><strong>Don't get angry for the small things</strong>. When you think how precious life is, you will start to see things differently. Don't take things so seriously. Consider LIFE seriously.</p>
<p><strong>A smile can open closed doors</strong>. You will feel better, live longer, make others feel better, have more friends, be less stressed... and so on and on and on. Smiling is SO powerful.</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p><a href="https://www.verywellmind.com/top-reasons-to-smile-every-day-2223755">Top Reasons to Smile Every Day</a></p>
</li>
<li>
<p><a href="https://www.waldenu.edu/online-bachelors-programs/bs-in-psychology/resource/the-power-of-smiling">The Power of Smiling</a></p>
</li>
</ul>
<h2>Conclusion</h2>
<p>There are countless life lessons that a child should know before they grow up. This post focuses on the importance of staying positive, being aware of your surroundings and learning how to be happy with what you have.</p>
<p>The list is definitely not exhaustive and it's up to you to decide what you think are the most important things for your child.</p>

    ]]></content>
  </entry>
	
  
  <entry>
    <title>How to raise smart kids</title>
    <link href="https://www.daddyandthekids.com/posts/how-to-raise-smart-kids/"/>
    <updated>2021-06-22T02:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>https://www.daddyandthekids.com/posts/how-to-raise-smart-kids/</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[
      <h1>How to Raise Smart Kids as a Dad (2021 Definitve Guide)</h1>
<p><img src="/images/How-To-Raise-Smart-Kids.jpg" alt="How To Raise Smart Kids" title="Credits to Ben White on https://unsplash.com/photos/qDY9ahp0Mto  "></p>
<h2>How Do You Recognise a Smart Kid?</h2>
<p>As parents, my friends and I are often talking about the development and growth of our children, and as a doctor I constantly got asked: &quot;<strong>How can we raise smart kids?</strong>&quot;</p>
<p>Now, first and foremost, &quot;being smart&quot; has a very wide meaning. I asked to many of my friends what they think a smart kid is, what defines a smart kid from &quot;less smart kids&quot; and that opens a lot of discussions and lets me see how different meanings this word can have to different people with unique backgrounds.</p>
<p>Many people often make the wrong assumption that &quot;smart&quot; equals &quot;good grades at school&quot;.
But psychology has shown repeatidly that this is not true. Yes, generally smart kids have good grades, but the opposite is not true at all. Many smart kids have bad grades because they are not engaged enough, or because of difficult situations.</p>
<p>So I will try to give this broad meaning to the word smart, based on what I learned, on my opinions and of answers I collected from friends.</p>
<p>Comment down below and tell me what you think.</p>
<p>I think that a <strong>smart kid</strong> is one that shows <strong>interest</strong>, <strong>curiosity</strong> in learning, a fast growing knowledge, that can make deductions and connections between pieces of knowledge he acquired.</p>
<p>Anyway the key here is <strong>curiosity</strong>: all kids are curious, so  <strong>all kids are smart</strong> . As a parent you want to <strong>enhance</strong> this curiosity and drive it a little bit to make your child explore things you think are important, but you also need to accomodate the things he likes. For example, if you think that learning a second language is important, make her curious about that by learning it yourself and telling her what you are doing. This is usually enough to trigger interest, if you sparkle with enthusiasm. And if you see that your boy has a particular interest in gardening, go on and indulge his curiosity and let him grow herbs and flowers in your balcony (please grow legal herbs, you don't want to end up on the news ;-) : &quot;Smart kid growing smart drugs: not so smart dad arrested&quot;  LOL :-D ).</p>
<p>I decided to avoid the word intelligent because that can open another rabbit hole about the types of intellingence... and maybe I'll write a post about that in the future.</p>
<p>In general every healthy average kid is a smart kid.
But more and more scientific studies show us that there are proven ways to make your kids smarter, and gathering the experience of &quot;smart&quot; parents is in line with science when it comes to define some methods that work.
So I read a lot and I talked to school educators as well as friend psichologists to figure out the best way to support children to enhance their already great mind skills.
There are some golden rules, some common sense pieces of knowledge, some strange tips, and some proven scientific ways.
Here they are in no particular orther of importance, so you keep reading till the end :-)</p>
<h2>How to Raise Smart Kids?</h2>
<h2>Your love will make your kids smarter</h2>
<p>Number one: <strong>hug your kids</strong> and play with them.
<strong>Start in the early childhood</strong>: show them that they are loved and taken care of, reduce stress (but set limits and learn how to say No the right way), talk a lot, smile, sing and play rhythms a lot, count things with them.</p>
<p>Try to avoid being negative.</p>
<p><strong>Do not yell</strong> at your kids. Yelling has the same effect of spanking, sometimes worse according to a study from the Harvard Medical School</p>
<blockquote>
<p>&quot;parental verbal abuse can injure brain pathways, possibly causing depression, anxiety, and problems with language processing&quot;.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Breathe deeply and stop for a second before you yell. If you don't, they will do like you soon.</p>
<p>Make your kids smarter by letting them <strong>develop empathy</strong>.</p>
<p>Teach them to <strong>express their feeling</strong> and teach them to try to <strong>guess other people's feelings</strong> just by looking at them. They will become more sensitive and more socially healthy. It will help them build good relationships. There are many super intelligent people with no empathy at all, and even if they end up doing great things, or being great leaders, they are not loved and sought after by their friends, they are usually scary unpleasant people, and if you love your kids you don't want them to be like this.</p>
<p>So for example, we were watching some news recently and they showed a building that was destroyed by a bomb. There was an old woman crying interviewed by the journalist and my elder son started to ask questions. So I took the opportunity to tell him: &quot; you see how sad she is, how hard it must be for her because her house was destroyed, she had lots of memomy and maybe worked hard for her to get it. What will she do now? &quot; to avoid too much strees to my kid I tried to invent some solutions: &quot;maybe her sons will help her build a new house. Maybe her friends will pay her for a beautiful hotel&quot;. You know just to give some hope and avoid desperation, even if life can be so hard, you want to train your little kids develop grit little by little and address them to a problem solving mindset.</p>
<p>Do not maltreat or insult your child. No parent is perfect, and we all have faults, but this point is not negotiable, no ifs and buts. Anyway you are here to learn how to make your kids smarter, so I think you are smart enough to know this.</p>
<h2>Read and Talk to Kids, to Make Them Smarter</h2>
<p><strong>Read books</strong> to your kids, at any age.
Start reading to toddlers even if they do not understand the words.</p>
<p>This gives them a head start in developing language skills.  Kids who are read to when young are more likely to develop a lifelong interest in reading, do well in school, and succeed in adult life.  Reading books is one of the most important activity that make kids smart. In addition, don't just  <strong>read to them, read</strong>  <strong><strong>with them</strong></strong>  . As they are growing analyse what you are reading, comment, ask them questions, listen to their opinions. Don't stop even when they are in high school, read with them some pages that you found interesting, maybe some philosophy passage, some newspaper editorial open to different interpretations or maybe a fun tale.</p>
<p><strong>Talk a lot</strong> to your child.</p>
<p>Tell them what you did  at work. Tell something about you when you were young. Preschool and school kids in particular love it. I always tell them something about my day and they love it. They keep asking for more. I admit, I am guilty of trying to catch their interest by always exaggerating my stories. But man, how they love it! They come running to me when I come back home screaming: DAD, WHAT DID YOU DO TODAY? I know sometimes it's a double edged sword, when you come home from work and you would just hang around and do nothing with a beer in your hand... but how can you resist to your kids being so happy?</p>
<p>Use <strong>active listening</strong> with your kids when they talk.</p>
<p>Kids who experienced more conversation at home have greater brain activity and verbal attitude. Ask questions and wait for responses. Engage in a two-way conversation.</p>
<p><strong>Tell stories</strong>.</p>
<p>For a whole year I put my kids to bed and I told them an invented soty in episode. It was a hard work for me, because I had to come up with new ideas every night, but kids don't judge you on the quality of your content they'll just eat out of your hand. I told them a story in episodes, with funny stupid things in it, sometimes with moral teachings, sometimes I took something that happend to me and transformed it into a story exaggerating and telling funny details. It was hard, because many nights after work I just wanted to relax, or I was uninspired and tired, but I think that these 10 minutes per night that I spent with them will be remembered for years. They were so into the story.</p>
<p>It was a creative effort for me to, since I blog and write songs, and always want to come up with new ideas, I think I got huge benefits too. Anyway you don't need to be crazy like me, you can also tell your kid about the fascinating things you experienced at the workplace (don't tell them how much your job sucks, please). Tell them about amazing childhood experiences. talk about the stories and analyse them to find out life lessons from you. Talk to your child about exactly how you fix problems in your everyday life as well as at work.</p>
<h2>Smart Kids Need to Play</h2>
<p><strong>Let your kid play</strong>. This is not just for fun. It's real development. Every baby animal plays. We see it in nature. And Play is a way to experiment, act real life situation to develop creativity. Play is the training ground for every human brain. Play can develop intellectual, social, physical and emotional skills. Children can play with everything. My kids can spend an afternoon at the beach with one empty plastic bottle and some pebbles. When you buy toys choose the one that can be used in multiple ways, or something that can help creativity and imagination.</p>
<p>Make your child <strong>learn a music instrument</strong>. Playing an instrument is a known secret to become smarter and more sensitive. Music improves memory and attention just by listening to it. The benefits are proven by science and the effects are long term. Plus, usually it's very fun if you don't push too hard</p>
<p><strong>Allow your child to get bored</strong>. According to Julia Robinson, Education and Training Director of the Independent Association of Prep Schools, it is okay for you child to get bored. Learning to be bored is part of preparing for adulthood. Your child should learn to enjoy “quiet reflection” instead of forcing him to fill his days with activities. Boredom can also trigger creative games.</p>
<p>Let your child <strong>play with other smart kids</strong>. Bad company can be detrimental to becoming smarter as much as being among the right people can benefit to that.</p>
<h2>Support Them and Be There to Make Your Kids Smarter</h2>
<p><strong>Be there, as a dad</strong>. Science has shown us that participating dads lower the risk that children will break the law when they grow up, drop out of school, end up in problematic relationships or that they'll have psychological problems.</p>
<p><strong>Do the smart things that you would like your kids do</strong>. Kids model our behavior.  When they see us reading books, writing, drawing a map of the house, designing a bathroom cabinet, making music, doing creative repairs in the house, helping our spouse in solving a problem, they will learn a lot and copy us. It works like magic, but only if you do your work smiling and being patient and calm.</p>
<p><strong>Encourage</strong> your kid’s <strong>creativity and problem solving</strong> as a whole. Creativity can be learned and developed.  Try exposing your child to paintings, classical music, dance.  Let him invent short stories. Let him try modeling crete. Let him paint and get dirty with acrilyc colors. Creativity can be thaught. Buy some books about creativity &lt;!— link —&gt; if you don't have a lot of ideas.</p>
<p><strong>Make your child responsible</strong> for his choices, to take some risks (not dangerous ones of course! Do not let him walk blindfolded on a rope between 2 skyscrapers!) and to fail but encourage him to keep on trying, avoid surrendering and to develop grit. Teach him to accept failure and to move on and try better the next time, improve something until he makes it. One of the first struggles for a kid is learning to ride a bike. This is usually a dad's job, to help him in the process. The right help can be a great boost in self-esteem. But, do not help him to much, allow your child to solve problems by himself. Just offer some hints or ask some questions that can trigger him in findign the answer on his own. Let him solve problems on his own so he learns from his experience. I know, it takes a lot of patience.</p>
<p>I wouldn't be surprised if scientific studies showed that the only secret to have smart kids is how much patience a dad has. I should study it further, surely there is some kind of positive correlation.</p>
<p><strong>Praise your child for his hard work</strong> and for their effort. Avoid compliments like &quot;you're so smart / you're so beautiful&quot; (of course use some grain of salt... sometimes you want to say to your daughter that she is beautiful, and sometimes you need to say to your kids that you appreciated how they solved this difficult problem because it shows they are intelligent). Anyway, praising your child for effort helps him to build confidence over his success and to engage in challenges.</p>
<p>But <strong>don’t praise your child too often</strong> because he may become a narcissist when he is older.  Give your child honest and feedback, encouragement and advice to make him improve the next time. This helps in raising a growth mindset.</p>
<p>According to psychiatrist Joe Brewster, kids should be encouraged to see learning as the process of becoming better at something, instead of having a fixed mind-set of his intelligence. When your child fails, he should see it as an opportunity for growth, instead of seeing himself as a failure.</p>
<p>It's healthy for kids experience failure and frustration sometimes. It develops grit.</p>
<p><strong>Set high expectations</strong> for your child. Tell them that you trust them and that you know they will do great things and be good people. Of course, don't exaggerate and force them to struggle for everything because they need to be number one.</p>
<p><strong>Avoid constantly correcting</strong> your child in every action she does or in difficult tasks. Let her discover things for herself, she will surprise you when she finds an unusual way to solve a problem.</p>
<p><strong>Make your child a responsible member of the family</strong>, give him things to do to help. My son loves vacuuming or glass cleaning.</p>
<p>Show your kid the <strong>importance of postponed satisfaction:</strong>  being able to resist the lure of immediate reward in order to obtain a bigger or far better incentive in the future pays off a lot. Researches reveal that being able to postpone satisfaction is one of one of the most effective individual attributes of successful individuals. It will enhance your kid's self control and train him to work hard to accomplish his goals. It also helps in your kid's financial education because you can educate your kid to save rather than spend small quantities of money on little things so that he can buy a bigger and more useful thing in the future. My kids loved it when I gave them a piggy bank as a present. They love putting coins in it and they treat it as their own treasure chest.</p>
<p><strong>Show up</strong> at your kids activities, have social interaction with other dads and families. I made great friends through my kids. Attend at sport events and recitals that your kids do.</p>
<h2>Good Health Matters</h2>
<p><strong>Physical exercise</strong> and <strong>outdoor activities</strong> are really important. Avoid too many sedentary activities. Toddlers, preschoolers and school kids have a lot of energy that needs to be burnt outside, otherwise they will start being nervous. If you find them jumping up and down your bed don't blame me. I told you! Exercise increases the flow of blood to the brain.</p>
<p><strong>Set a limit on TV</strong>. Both in time and in content. Also avoid TV and screens in general before age 2. I realized that my kids (one in particular) become nervous after a TV session of more than an hour. The problem with on demand shows and pay TV is that you have unlimited streams of content. Binging is very easy and instant gratifications pours showers of dopamine on your kids neurons so that turning off the TV is very painful for them, and can lead to crises and nervousness that in some really extreme cases can resemble a mild withdrawal syndrome.</p>
<p>Educate your kids on the importance of <strong>eating healhy foods</strong>. Generally, common sense is enough, you know, a good balance between proteins, carbohydrates and healthy fats. Fruit and vegetables in good quantities, avoiding overprocessed foods, eating enough and not too much, limiting simple sugars. Limiting salt.</p>
<p><strong>Avoid the use of smartphones or tablets</strong>. They have negative effects.  Researchers found that “routine and frequent use of mobile devices appear to be associated with behavioral problems in childhood.” <a href="https://www.cune.edu/academics/resource-articles/examining-effect-smartphones-child-development"> The Effect of Smartphones on Child Development | CUNE Online</a>  .  The World Health Organization (WHO) has begun identifying the risks associated with children using smartphone technology. In my opinion you should ask some question to why a smartphone screen has such an hypnotizing and soothing effect on a crying baby. It's scary how easy you can calm a baby or keep him busy with this little device. But what education are you giving to your kid? What are you teaching to him by giving him a screen? You turn off a dialogue and subsitute with an instant easy gratification. It's scary again and can lead to dangerous choices in the future if your child get used to this kind of thinking. Moreover it's so sad to see families on restaurant that keep kids busy with a phone instead of telling a joke or trying to entertain them, or even give them the priviledge to experience boredom.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Children need to learn how to self-soothe and manage their emotions. And if they’re frequently handed these devices, they don’t learn these things. —   <strong>Jean Twenge, a psychologist and author of  &quot;iGen&quot;</strong></p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Parents must consider what image they express to their children and how they communicate responsible smartphone consumption. <a href="https://www.theatlantic.com/magazine/archive/2018/07/the-dangers-of-distracted-parenting/561752/"> Parents’ Screen Time Is Hurting Kids The Atlantic</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>So in the end, if you give your kid a tablet or a phone, do it for a limited amunt of time, in your presence, and use educational apps that teach maths, letters, words, music. Something challenging for the mind but not too stressful. My son found a chess game and he liked it so much. Chess is not super easy in the beginning but for a 7 to 9 years old is excellent. The pace of the game is not too fast, but it's enough entertaining. There are also some logic strategy board games that are great, like <strong><a href="https://www.amazon.co.uk/gp/product/B00001NTXN/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=1634&amp;creative=6738&amp;creativeASIN=B00001NTXN&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=dominic8004-21&amp;linkId=05b323ab65196e4c7969dfcd0eb09859">QUORIDOR</a></strong></p>
<h2>Good Sleep Makes Smarter Kids</h2>
<p>The correlation between liveliness and intellingence in kids and the <strong>quantity and quality of sleep</strong> they get is known since I was a child. If it matters, there are a studies that showed a correlation in the amount of sleep and grades. Lack of sleep in adults can accelerate aging and increase the risk of dementia. In kids missing an hour of sleep can turn a sixth grader’s brain into a fourth grader. In general poor sleep does not seem to have an impact on overall intelligence in children, but more on attention and behavuior, these 3 meta-analyses are a balanced starting point to explore the topic:</p>
<p><a href="%5Bhttps://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/29776624/%5D(https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/29776624/)">Cognition and objectively measured sleep duration in children: a systematic review and meta-analysis</a></p>
<p><a href="%5Bhttps://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/22545685/%5D(https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/22545685/)">Sleep, cognition, and behavioral problems in school-age children: a century of research meta-analyzed</a></p>
<p><a href="%5Bhttps://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/30660750/%5D(https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/30660750/)">A review of developmental consequences of poor sleep in childhood</a></p>
<p>If you <strong>smoke</strong> (quit as soon as possible for you and your kids, man we are in 2021, smoking sucks), <strong>do not smoke around your kid</strong>. Kids of smoking families and kids who breathe secondhand smoke are more likely to smoke when they grow up. I also read online that they may risk more mental problems in the future but I had not time to verify this piece of information and I am a little skeptical about it, because it is also very vague. I will expand if I found something useful.</p>
<h2>More Food for the Brain of Smart Kids</h2>
<p>Do simple <strong>maths games</strong>. Calculate change with them when you pay something.</p>
<p>Consider introducing your child early to <strong>coding</strong>. It's the future, man. If you don't know anything about it, it's time for you to learn it too. There are great resources for free online, like www.freecodecamp.org , or <a href="https://code.org/"> Learn today, build a brighter tomorrow. | Code.org</a>  or even great youtube channels that go step by step , there are tons. Coding helps problem solving, logic and high level thinking. And some of the highest paying jobs are in the tech field.</p>
<p>Expose your kid to a <strong>second language</strong>. If you have a foreigner babysitter tell her to only talk in their native language. Maybe you can have your kids watch cartoons in another language. Use apps like Duolingo, watch together youtube videos that teache a second language. Listen to audiobooks for kids in that language, best if done while reading the book at the same time and trying to read and repeat the sounds (a technique called shadowing speeds up a lot the process of learning a good pronunciation).</p>
<p>Ensure that <strong>lifelong leaning</strong> is your goal and also the whole family's goal, not just a school obligation.</p>
<p><strong>Imagine with your child</strong>, and make it a vivid dream, their bright and fulfilling future, let them tell you what they'd love and amplify that dream by adding details, and tell them the steps they need to do to get there. For example my daughter often says she wants to literally build her skyscraper office where she's gonna be the boss at the last floor. So I amplify this telling her that she needs to have a nice view over a beautiful park, and in her job she will help thousand of people, because she will be a good leader, not only a boss. And that to get there she needs to study, love learning, start small and work hard... you know, don't kill their dreams, self fulfilling prophecies happen.</p>
<p>Watch or <strong>read the news together and comment</strong>.</p>
<p>When you fail at something, big or small, don't get nervous and show them how to embrace mistakes and how to get up again and to improve.</p>
<p><strong>Play chess</strong> together.</p>
<p>Tell them about your <strong>values</strong> and act accordingly to them.</p>
<p><strong>Let your child teach you something</strong> that they learnt. This builds self-confidence in him, forces him to develop language skills and makes him realise if there are parts he did not understand. Like Feynman sais, the best way to learn something is to teach it to others. If you don't understan something ask him questions and try to help him rephrase the sentence. When they show you something they did, ask them: &quot;show me how you did&quot;, it works like magic in boosting your child self-confidence.</p>
<p>&lt;!—
<a href="https://www.businessinsider.com/12-ways-to-raise-smarter-more-successful-and-happier-kids-2019-8?r=US&amp;IR=T#2-show-them-how-to-embrace-mistakes-2">https://www.businessinsider.com/12-ways-to-raise-smarter-more-successful-and-happier-kids-2019-8?r=US&amp;IR=T#2-show-them-how-to-embrace-mistakes-2</a></p>
<p>—&gt;</p>
<h2>Conclusion</h2>
<p>There you have it. This is what came to my mind, what I researched for. You can add your tips in the comments below. I will slowly add and link to the scientific papers I used, so consider this post a work in progress.</p>
<p>This is not perfect and I don't always think about doing everything that's written here as a dad. I make a lot of mistakes like every dad, but I always try to improve. I have a good experience with my 3 kids of different ages, and I always learn something new because every baby is different, and every time is different. I also changed over my 9 years of fatherhood. But I realize that I do most of the things posted here in bits and pieces. I am not obsessive, I prefer a more relaxed life, but many of these things come natural to me. I am always grateful to my wife for her support, because everything is easier whe you have a smart wife. And honestly, the mother of your kids matters as much as you, in fact probably a lot more, in raising smart kids. So the best results come from the cooperation of both parents.</p>
<p>I think that when you spend time with your kids, most of these things will happen naturally. Time is precious, kids grow fast and society forces different rhythms on us. Learn to be a juggler with your time!</p>

    ]]></content>
  </entry>
	
</feed>
